accused
of hacking into Pentagon and Nazi
systems. 40 million credit card and
debit number stolen.
>> On its surface, the International Space
Station heats up to 120° C.
The onboard temperature and humidity
control system keeps the inside at the
right temperature for human survival.
If it fails, the astronauts stationed
here would literally be cooked. And just
now, a hacker has gotten hold of the
system software.
He's not a hostile government agent,
just a 15-year-old in his bedroom. He
successfully gained access to 13 NASA
computers.
This teenager is a prodigy, one of the
most talented young hackers the world
has ever seen.
And he didn't just break into NASA, he
also hacked the Pentagon.
From his point of view, he's just toying
around.
From the government's perspective, he's
a national security threat.
>> Largest identity theft case ever.
>> Largest data breach in US history
>> that affected millions of people.
>> One that humiliated them over and over
again and one that they will go after
ruthlessly.
[Music]
Confirmed.
It's the year 1989, a suburban village
in South Florida.
This is Jonathan James. He is 6 years
old.
While other kids are outside playing
tag, he's busy inside, glued to the
family's computer. Mostly, he's just
playing games. His parents are worried
about his obsession. His dad is a
programmer. At one point, he installs
parental protection on the computer, but
Jonathan just breaks through it.
In his early teens, he starts reading
books in the programming language C and
the operating system Unix, a precursor
for Linux and Mac OS. He studies source
code extensively and talks to other
computer enthusiasts.
He spends countless hours in front of
the computer, often until late into the
night.
One afternoon, Jonathan uninstalls
Windows from his family PC, then
installs Linux. No one asked him to. No
one could stop him.
His computer time regularly leads to
arguments with his parents. It doesn't
get any better once he gets his own PC.
After a while, his parents decide to
confiscate it. Jonathan runs away and
says he's not coming home until he gets
it back.
Soon it won't be his parents who are
trying to keep him away from a computer,
but the US government.
[Applause]
[Music]
At 15, Jonathan has long morphed from
curious pre-teen to full-blown hacker,
one of the youngest and best at the
time. Online, he's known under his
alias, Comrade. Jonathan really enjoys
messing with systems, not to break them,
but to beat them. It's a power thing, a
control thing. He likes the thrill of
it. The tougher the system, the more it
pulls him in. He goes in, proves it's
not so secure after all, and moves on.
He doesn't care much about the stuff
inside. He doesn't steal data, delete
files, or spread viruses. In fact,
sometimes he does the opposite. He'll
break in, then send a polite little
email to the system admin. Hey, your
setup's got holes. Here's where. Here's
how to fix it.
[Music]
In the summer of 1999, Jonathan is
looking for a new challenge. So, he
decides to hack NASA, more specifically
the AY's Marshall Space Flight Center in
Huntsville, Alabama.
He gains access to 13 NASA computers.
It's unclear how, and this time,
Jonathan decides to actually take
something. He downloads proprietary
software valued at $1.7 million.
It's the software for the temperature
and humidity control of the ISS.
In an interview, Jonathan will later
say, "The code itself was crappy.
Certainly not worth $1.7 million like
they claimed. The only reason I was
downloading the source code in the first
place was because I was studying C
programming. And what better way to
learn than reading software written by
the government."
Just downloading the software didn't
give Jonathan remote control over the
ISS systems. Having the source code is
one thing, but actually sending commands
to his spacecraft is a whole different
story. It would have taken more steps to
actually access the system. But this
hack is still a massive security breach.
When NASA finds out, they have to shut
down their systems for 3 weeks,
resulting in damages of around $40,000.
Two months later, Jonathan takes up his
next challenge, hacking the Pentagon.
More specifically, their Defense Threat
Reduction Agency. It analyzes and deals
with potential threats to the US from
nuclear, chemical, and biological
weapons.
Jonathan gains access to a server in
Bellis, Virginia, and installs a back
door. Again, it is unknown how he
actually pulled this off. Once inside
DTR systems, he intercepts more than
3,300 messages to and from DTR staff. He
retrieves 19 usernames and passwords of
employees, at least 10 of which have
access to military computers.
Jonathan thinks his hacks are no big
deal. To him, they are quote just
harmless exploration. Law enforcement
disagrees.
[Music]
It's an early morning in January 2000.
Last month, Jonathan turned 16. By now,
he has not one but multiple computers of
his own. He is well connected with other
hackers, sharing tips and tricks. He
also loves Star Trek. His mother comes
into the room and wakes him up.
>> Jonathan, honey, the FBI is at the door.
>> They're here for him.
They raid his family home and take five
computers. They also take his Palm
Pilot, some CDs, and his Star Trek book.
Bull choice for evidence.
Jonathan is questioned by the officers.
He admits everything and promises to
never do it again. Then he hears nothing
for 3 months.
And then the authorities press charges
and his life begins to change
dramatically.
Jonathan James becomes the youngest
person ever convicted of violating cyber
crime laws in the US. If Jonathan had
been an adult, he might have ended up
with a decade behind bars, but he's
still a minor. So, the US District Court
in Miami puts him on 6 months house
arrest.
Jonathan is no longer allowed to use his
computers in his free time, and even
worse, he has to write letters of
apology to NASA and the Department of
Defense. Later, he tests positive for
drugs. a clear probation violation. So,
he gets sent to a juvenile detention
facility for 6 months. He's scared about
spending time there with actual
criminals.
His father will later say that prison
changed Jonathan. It made him strangely
idle.
Looking back, Jonathan regrets the whole
thing. What started as fun challenges
ended with him behind bars. The thrills
weren't worth it. Not even close. From
that point on, he decides to leave
hacking behind for good. But not
everyone believes him. And a few years
later, his past life will catch up with
him.
Some viewers think our animations are
made with AI. Our 3D artists, who spend
countless hours building these shots
from scratch, aren't angry, just
disappointed. AI can be helpful with
other tasks, though, like research.
That's where Merlin AI comes in. Merlin
AI is an all-in-one AI tool that bundles
the best AI models all in one place, and
you can even save tons of money. They
gave us a 75% discount code we will
share with you in just a second. You
might already be using AI to rewrite
emails or to figure out what it really
means when your ex texts you up at 1:00
a.m. But Merlin goes beyond that. In our
work as journalists, it helps us with
research, summarizing dense papers, and
pulling reference images in one click.
Once installed, it's like a competent
assistant in your browser. If you want
to try Merlin AI, you can get a huge
discount right now. While other AI tools
charge around $20 per month for just one
model, Merlin AI gives you access to all
major ones for only $5 per month. Click
on the link in the description and use
our code fern at checkout or scan the QR
code.
[Music]
This is Albert Gonzalez. He's got a few
things in common with Jonathan James. He
was also born in the8s. He too is a
self-taught hacker. When he was 14, he
also broke into NASA systems. And as a
consequence, he also got a visit by the
FBI.
But that didn't stop Gonzalez from
hacking. Far from it. We don't know if
Albert Gonzalez and Jonathan James knew
each other, but they had a common hacker
friend called Christopher Scott.
Gonzalez went by many aliases on the
internet, but his favorite was Soup
Nazi, a reference to a Seinfeld episode.
>> You want bread?
>> Yes, please.
>> $3.
>> In early 2000s, Gonzalez stumbled across
Shadow Crew, a marketplace for
trafficking stolen credit and bank card
numbers and identity information. And
even though the feds are having an eye
on him, he gets involved.
In 2003, he gets caught trying to pull
cash from an ATM using fake credit
cards. To avoid jail time, he agrees to
work with the Secret Service. Soon, he
helps them bust a bunch of shadow crew
members. You'd expect that his work as
an informant for the Secret Service
would stop him from any criminal
activity. But well, in his view, the
salary from the Secret Service is too
low. So, he gets back to what he does
best, hacking. He sets up an elaborate
scheme he calls get rich or die trying.
The scheme will turn into one of the
world's biggest cases of identity theft.
It'll ruin his life, but Jonathan James
will end up dead.
[Music]
This is Scott, who is both friends with
Gonzalez and James. Next to him, said
someone who, according to criminal
reports, is only known as JJ.
They're doing something called war
driving. It's a simple technique. You
drive around in your car and park close
to companies. You only need your laptop
and a high power radio antenna. Once
you're close enough, you check for
vulnerabilities in their Wi-Fi network.
Back then, most companies weren't
exactly taking cyber security seriously.
Inside Office Max, people are buying
Post-its and whiteboard markers in four
colors, gearing up for a meeting that
probably could have been an email.
Outside, Scott and JJ access the store's
Wi-Fi and through that enter its
systems. Once inside, they install a
sniffer program which captures and
downloads credit and debit card data
from customers.
Then they send the data to Gonzalez. He
forwards it to another hacker who
decrypts the PIN codes. Gonzalez and his
crew don't just sell the stolen card
info. They encode them onto blank
magnetic strip cards and use those to
pull tens of thousands of dollars out of
ATMs.
After the Office Max breach, banks were
apparently forced to reissue around
200,000 cards. And this hack wasn't a
one-off. Over the span of the next three
years, Gonzalez and his crew hack into
several major US companies, including
BJ's Wholesale Club, Boston Market,
Barnes & Noble, Forever 21, and others.
Their biggest credit card data heist
happens at TJX. That's the parent
company of TJ Maxx, Marshalls,
HomeGoods, and others. Around 96 million
TJX customers are affected by the theft
of their credit and debit card info.
At the time, these attacks make up the
largest case of identity theft in US
history. The crew stole the data of
around 180 million credit and debit
cards. The total damage of all infected
companies amounts to roughly $400
million US in reimbursements, legal
costs, and forensic fees.
>> There's a major break in a credit card
scam that affected millions of people.
Experts say this man's arrest may lead
to the kingpin behind the biggest credit
card ID theft in history.
The Secret Service investigates and at
one point they realize that their very
own informant is not only involved but
is a mastermind behind the TJX heist.
May 2008, Pinerest, Florida. Jonathan
James is 24 years old now.
[Music]
He doesn't go to college. He doesn't
have a job. His mother died of breast
cancer 6 years ago.
Together with his brother, he still
lives in the house he grew up in.
He apparently suffers from depression.
Overall, he's living a withdrawn life
and is retired from hacking.
But today, he'll get another surprise
visit.
This time, it's the Secret Service. They
raid the family's house just like the
FBI had done 8 years ago.
They drew a connection from Gonzalez to
Christopher Scott to him. They suspect
that JJ is short for Jonathan James and
that he's part of the hacker group. The
agents go through Jonathan's stuff.
They find a suicide note he had written
years ago and a gun.
We don't know if the agents offer him
psychological help, but according to
Jonathan, they don't confiscate the
weapon.
[Music]
Jonathan is shocked. He swears that he
has nothing to do with the TJX case.
What's going on?
On the subpoena, he's able to find some
answers. He reads about this guy, Albert
Gonzalez.
Jonathan recognizes him by another
nickname he used online.
Gonzalez has been working as an
informant for the feds since 2003. For 5
years, Gonzalez used Scott to pull off
his hacks while simultaneously writing
out other hackers to the feds to stay in
their good graces.
Jonathan is sure that Gonzalez is now
trying to pin the hacks on Scott.
and he is getting a bad feeling. He
thinks they'll be a much more appealing
target than Chris.
It might not matter to the feds that
he's innocent. Even though, in his
words, Scott and Gonzalez are the most
destructive, dangerous hackers the feds
ever caught. They'll let them off easy
because he's a juicier target. That
would please the public more.
In Jonathan's mind, the picture is
clear. They need a scapegoat. Not
Gonzalez, not Scott, not the one who
actually caused the damage, but him,
Jonathan.
In his words, the feds played dirty. He
holds these beliefs for a reason.
There's this paper that has made rounds
in the hacker scene, Agent Steel's Guide
to Getting Busted. It's basically a
survival guide for hackers written by
one who ended up in prison.
Agent Steel's real name was Justin
Tanner Peterson. He was an American
hacker who worked as an informant for
the feds while continuing to commit
crimes.
Agent Steel writes, "The criminal
justice system is a game to be played
both by prosecution and defense. And if
you have to be a player, you'd be wise
to learn the rules of engagement." He
makes it clear that law enforcement
isn't always fair. They play dirty and
will do just about anything, including
lie, to win their case.
Jonathan read this guide and he knows
that Gonzalez is working with the feds,
so he's convinced he's going to prison
even though he's innocent.
The first time was already terrifying.
He doesn't want to go through that
again.
[Music]
On May 18th, 2008, 2 weeks after agents
raided his home, Jonathan was found dead
in his home after a self-inflicted
gunshot wound.
[Music]
He wrote a note. There are messages to
his family and friends, passwords to his
accounts. In this letter, he also
expresses his opinion on the
authorities. He writes, "I have no faith
in the justice system. Perhaps my
actions today in this letter will send a
stronger message to the public. Either
way, I have lost control over the
situation, and this is my only way to
regain control." Remember,
it's not whether you win or lose. It's
whether I win or lose. And sitting in
jail for 20, 10, or even 5 years for a
crime I didn't commit is not me winning.
I die free.
[Music]
In March 2010, Albert Gonzalez was
sentenced to 20 years in federal prison
for his role in the series of hacks. In
the backyard of his parents, the Secret
Service seized a barrel containing $1.2
2 million in cash. Christopher Scott was
sentenced to 7 years in prison for his
role in the attacks. It's likely that
the pseudonym JJ didn't refer to
Jonathan James, but rather to Steven
Watt, another figure convicted in the
TJX case, who was known to use the alias
Jim Jones online.
[Music]
At the point of his death, Jonathan
neither had been arrested, charged,
tried, nor sentenced. It seems like
knowing that Gonzalez had worked with
the Secret Service fueled Jonathan's
fear to become a scapegoat and end up in
prison.
Jonathan James wasn't some criminal
mastermind. He was a teenager with a
rare talent and a deep curiosity for how
systems work. After he hacked into them,
he often offered to help fix them.
Instead of guiding such talents, helping
to channel them into something good, the
justice system decided to make an
example out of him.
[Music]